<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Vertette's Blog</title>
        <link>https://vertette.github.io/</link>
        <description>A blog about game design and development.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>All material (c) Christopher Stephens 2023 unless stated otherwise</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Magic of Starfield]]></title>
            <link>https://vertette.github.io/post/magicstarfield</link>
            <guid>https://vertette.github.io/post/magicstarfield</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Since the dawn of humanity, we've marvelled at the stars, wondering "what could be out there?" The answers we have right now might not even be that exciting, bu...]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Since the dawn of humanity, we've marvelled at the stars, wondering &quot;what could be out there?&quot; The answers we have right now might not even be that exciting, but the fascination we have with space continues anyway. The unknown never stops being interesting, and space is either an infinite unknown or very close to it. And like many of humanity's most thought-provoking questions like &quot;what would you do if the world fell apart tomorrow&quot; and &quot;what if vikings were real&quot;, Bethesda made a game that taps into that very human question: <em>Starfield</em>.</p>
<p><em>Starfield</em>, too, is very fascinating. Not so much because of what it is, but what it represents. Like Bethesda's past single player games, <a href="https://www.metacritic.com/game/the-elder-scrolls-v-skyrim/"><em>Skyrim</em></a> and <a href="https://www.metacritic.com/game/fallout-4/"><em>Fallout 4</em></a>, it received <a href="https://www.metacritic.com/game/starfield/">a lot of favorable reviews from critics</a> and seems to have sold <a href="https://twitter.com/BethesdaStudios/status/1704246639970369954">a healthy amount of copies</a>, yet Bethesda's fans seem rather sharply divided - moreso than usual - over a game that, on the surface, seems very similar to the studio's output over the past decade, and a lot of the criticism that can be found about the game online is scattershot. There doesn't seem to be a clear consensus on what exactly the game should've done, but a lot of the criticism do draw from the same well, whether directly or indirectly: <em>Starfield</em> is a game that fundamentally does not play to Bethesda's strengths as a studio. In simpler terms? The problem is the setting.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/starfield_planet.jpg" alt="A screenshot of a planet in Starfield" />
<em>To boldly... wait, I've seen those exact same rock spires two minutes ago.</em></p>
<p>So what are Bethesda's strengths? Well, if nothing else, their games can be very immersive and engaging, and no other developer makes a game quite like they do (and QA testers across the world are thankful for that every day). It's hard to sum up their design philosophy in one sentence, and it's probably pretentious of me to try and do so anyway, but here it is: &quot;let the player do whatever they want, whenever they want, with no wrong choices, in a world that feels believably big&quot;. The past decade of Bethesda games have added &quot;and must be playable until the end of time&quot; to that philosophy on top. It's a design philosophy that has resulted in a lot of well-beloved games that have gotten a lot of praise for their immersive qualities and environmental storytelling and also <em>Fallout 76</em>, but there are flaws with this mentality that aren't inherently obvious. For now, let's focus on the &quot;believably big&quot; part of that equation.</p>
<p>Bethesda's games employed a lot of procedurally generated content back in Ye Olden Times, and it has made an uncelebrated return ever since <em>Skyrim</em>. There is nothing inherently wrong with the use of procedurally generated content, it's just that <em>Starfield</em>'s use of it is so poor that people denounce it on sight. Simulating even a small part of the universe is a big task, and it makes sense to use procedurally generated content to make the universe feel believably big while making sure the game can release before <em>Star Citizen</em>'s release and the heat death of the universe, whichever comes first. Half of the problem is the setting: all the planets in Starfield are flat, uniform and mostly devoid of life. Humanity's colonization of the stars seems to have been somewhat unsuccessful going by how few non-bandit people you find out there, and what little alien life there is can't be talked to. That's realistic, but it seems Bethesda has forgotten what's most important: what does that do for gameplay? The answer seems to have been nothing. There are plenty of obvious mechanics that would fit well in a harsher and more realistic science-fiction setting like this, and yet the game doesn't seem to care that much in exploring them outside of a select few like zero-gravity combat. Survival mechanics were apparently more of a factor during development <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZNQzIjptC_o">according to Todd Howard himself</a>, but as he explains, they &quot;nerfed the hell out of it&quot;. Why would you <em>not</em> want to sell your new franchise's setting through its gameplay?</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/starfield_atlantis.jpg" alt="A screenshot of New Atlantis in Starfield" />
<em>New Atlantis marks the first time in a Bethesda game where the crowds felt somewhat dense. Maybe I'm a sociopath, but I will never get tired of shooting into the air and watching people scramble.</em></p>
<p>To circle back to Bethesda's design philosophy, the problem with &quot;no wrong choices&quot; means that you will inevitably end up with very shallow roleplaying, which is a common criticism their recent games receive. Why can I walk into Solitude as an Imperial without issue? Why do I even have the option of building scrapyards when I'm supposed to be looking for my son? Why can I be the leader of every faction at once, even if they're supposed to be hostile towards each other? The list goes on. These games are too afraid to tell the player &quot;no&quot; or to give players a wrong choice. The problem with that philosophy is that while it makes their games very easy to pick up, play and put down, it also means that the world feels very player-centric and fake. The quality of Bethesda's writing has also not been a huge priority for some time now, so by design, their worlds are almost completely reliant on their art and music teams to pull you into the world. Before <em>Starfield</em>, Bethesda were the masters at this. In contrast, <em>Starfield</em>'s setting severely limits how crazy and alien their planets can be. How does the studio that put out <em>Morrowind</em> fail so badly at making another alien feeling setting when that's literally what the game should be about?</p>
<p>The other half of the problem is the technology, which is so outdated even for Bethesda standards that it's shocking a modern AAA game released in this state, which is saying something in our current industry. The planets seem to make use of 2D noise distribution to generate stuff, a technique so outdated for terrain generation <em>Minecraft</em> ditched it back in Alpha, with zero artist defined rules used to generate anything. That's how you end up with the exact same ruin models spawning at the same coordinates on every planet with the same enemy spawn locations every time. Then there's space travel, which feels completely disjointed from everything else as you don't actually use it to travel. Seamless travel between space and planets is impossible in <em>Starfield</em>. The best way to get around is quick travelling through menus and sitting through loading screens, which are everywhere. They're so jarring it kills the last bits of immersion the game would've otherwise had. When you compare it to other games like <em>No Man's Sky</em> or even the unreleased <em>Star Citizen</em>, it's almost impressive just how last-gen it feels in comparison.</p>
<p>So you have an AAA game with a boring setting and some jank, big whoop, lots of AAA games do. The problem is that that sense of immersion, that magic that drew people into Bethesda's previous games, is almost completely gone from <em>Starfield</em> as a result. There's no sense of discovery when you encounter the same bases with the same enemies on a samey looking planet. There's no wonder in travelling through space by menus. What you're left with is a game that had a lot of talent behind it, but ends up feeling like less than the sum of its parts. All of the games' flaws - the wildly fluctuating writing quality, shallow mechanics, perfectly acceptable combat and jank - aren't new for Bethesda, but without that magic to immerse the player they're much more prominent this time around.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/starfield_space.jpg" alt="A screenshot of space in Starfield" />
<em>The scale of space is such a hard thing to capture in a video game, it almost makes you wonder why Bethesda insisted on trying so hard. I'd trade in a thousand boring planets for twenty interesting ones.</em></p>
<p>So then why <em>did</em> Bethesda insist on this setting that creatively limits them so much, and then not at least mine it for gameplay mechanics? Obviously I can't prove this for certain, but my suspicion is that this was done entirely for pragmatic reasons. After all, Bethesda games have never been about what kind of interesting mechanics you could mine out of their settings, but about what kind of setting would fit with the mechanics they want to include, and I imagine <em>Starfield</em> was the same way. You can't exactly call this game focused on its &quot;hard&quot; sci-fi setting when you literally gain magic space powers throughout the story. The tech behind <em>Starfield</em>, as I went into earlier, is rather simplistic and outdated, but seeing how much content there is in the game, it's clearly not half-assed. My guess is these simple, uniform and flat planets and disjointed travel really was the best Bethesda could do in a reasonable timeframe and budget, so the setting ended up matching what the tech can do and they didn't think it was that important for these features to be improved upon. <em>Starfield</em> seems much less interested in simulating an entire universe for you to explore and more interested in making the universe feel big while you're off on goofy space adventures with your crew, and while those goofy space adventures <em>is</em> where the game shines the brightest, it had to sacrifice a lot to get there. I don't want to say they should have been less ambitious, because God knows we could use more of that in this industry, but it's clear they swallowed much more than they could digest.</p>
<p>In that way, <em>Starfield</em> might be the most important game Bethesda has made since <em>Skyrim</em>. It shows exactly where their strengths and their weaknesses lie. It shows exactly what people love about their games and what people hate. Most importantly, it shows just how important good technology is to deliver a creative vision. Let's just hope Bethesda realizes all that too.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>vertettegd@gmail.com (Vertette)</author>
            <category>Design</category>
            <enclosure url="https://vertette.github.io/img/starfield_space.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Identity of Yooka-Laylee]]></title>
            <link>https://vertette.github.io/post/identityyookalaylee</link>
            <guid>https://vertette.github.io/post/identityyookalaylee</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[How do you make a spiritual successor stand out?  A spiritual successor (or a homage, clone, rip-off, whatever you want to call it) is very much a double-edged...]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>How do you make a spiritual successor stand out?</p>
<p>A spiritual successor (or a homage, clone, rip-off, whatever you want to call it) is very much a double-edged sword for game developers. On one hand it doesn't take much thought or experimentation to design them, but on the other hand, how exactly do you give these kinds of games their own identity so that they can stand out on their own? This is particularly an issue for indie developers, because the lower budget guarantees that you will never be able to match the original in aspects like polish or visuals.</p>
<p>Back in 2015, many a 3D platformer fan - myself included - were left hungering for a new game. <em>Super Mario 3D World</em> came out two years before, and while it was fine, the problem with it was that that's all there is to say about it. I'm not even going into detail about <em>Sonic Lost World</em>, and I genuinely can't recall a single 3D platformer that released in 2014. Enter <em>Project Ukulele</em>, a new project from <em>Playtonic Games</em>, a new developer consisting of a few unsatisified Rare employees. A few months later, <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/playtonic/yooka-laylee-a-3d-platformer-rare-vival"><em>Yooka-Laylee</em> launched its crowdfunding campaign</a> and quickly broke Kickstarter records as it became the fastest game on the platform to receive a million US dollars at the time. Clearly the hunger for new 3D platformers was alive and strong, yet the game itself released a few years later to much worse reception. <a href="https://www.metacritic.com/game/yooka-laylee/">Critics were apathetic</a>, consumers were mixed and while the franchise still has its fans, it quickly faded out of the public consciousness. Not even the release of <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/846870/YookaLaylee_and_the_Impossible_Lair/">a much better received spin-off</a> or <a href="https://www.nintendolife.com/news/2021/11/playtonics-original-yooka-laylee-game-is-getting-a-follow-up-title">the announcement of a sequel</a> was enough to bring <em>Yooka-Laylee</em> back into the spotlight.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/yooka_achievements.png" alt="Yooka-Laylee and the Impossible Lair's Steam achievement list, with the 'beat the game' achievement sitting at a 6.1% obtain rate" />
<em>While I have talked with many people who like The Impossible Lair, I haven't talked with many people who actually beat it. The final level taking somewhere between 30 to 45 minutes might be a reason.</em></p>
<p>So what exactly went wrong with <em>Yooka-Laylee</em>? Well, whatever obvious criticism you may or may not have about the original game, <em>The Impossible Lair</em> or the franchise in general, the biggest problem it faces is less obvious - it never got to step outside of Rare's shadow.</p>
<p>One easy way to make your spiritual successor stand out is to theme it around something different. <em>Banjo-Kazooie</em> has a clear fairy tale theme, with a cast of talking animals, fairies, pirates, and whatever Klungo is as well as <a href="https://youtu.be/-mov342gII4?t=11700">a slightly grim sense of humor</a>. A magician with skull for a face uses magic powers to transform you into crazy forms which you then use to rescue your sister from a nasty old witch, complete with broom and talking pot who assures her that she is the prettiest girl in the land. In contrast, I have no clue if <em>Yooka-Laylee</em> was even supposed to have a theme. The two main characters are a lizard and a bat (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9mSzJj1c1z0">what's up with that?</a>), and while their designs are good, I can't tell you how they're supposed to fit in with a low-poly dinosaur, a vending machine with a face, a skeleton in a pot, a duck with his head in a jar and a bee in a business suit.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/yooka_rap.jpg" alt="A line-up of Yooka-Laylee characters from the Yooka-Laylee Rap video" />
<em>I know this gripe is super minor, but how come they never added the Yooka-Laylee rap to the game? Seems like a waste to just keep it on YouTube.</em></p>
<p>The plot of the game involves having to save Yooka and Laylee's book from said bee, who uses a machine to steal it for unknown reasons, which also doesn't quite gel together. If your main characters are animals and the villain is a CEO, having him bulldoze the forest where Yooka and Laylee live to make way for tacky souvenir shops and trendy coffee stores seems like a much more obvious fit. The villain doesn't even get his own army of corporate drones, overworked salarymen, henchmen in suits or anything like that, instead you just mostly fight gremlins. One of the bosses in this game is a <em>wall with a face</em>. Another is an <em><strong>ice block with a face</strong></em>.</p>
<p>What especially gets my goat about <em>Yooka-Laylee</em>'s setting is that all the levels are contextualized as books, and the act of collecting Pagies and using them to expand the worlds fits well with that, yet all the environments, while pretty, are mostly bog-standard platformer worlds. Jungle, snow, swamp, casino... where's the fantasy world with castles, dragons and knights? The sci-fi world where you jump across flying cars and glowing skyscrapers? The noire world where everything's in black and white and you investigate crimes? The game simply never utilizes this potential, which feels like a waste of a good idea. At least the environments use unique setpieces, like the tribal structures of Tribalstack Tropics, the ice castles of Glitterglaze Glacier and the giant gambling machines of Capital Cashino... all of which the next game, <em>The Impossible Lair</em>, never uses. It does have plenty of ordinary towns, forests and factories however, like a typical platformer setting. While there's nothing wrong with that per sé, the result ends up looking like a game from a completely different franchise.</p>
<p>Of course themes, characters and settings aren't everything. The best way to make your spiritual successor truly stand out is to change the moment-to-moment gameplay. It doesn't even have to be in a major way, just some new mechanic that changes how players approach obstacles is enough, say by adding a dash move, a rolling move, a grappling hook... <em>Yooka-Laylee</em> and <em>The Impossible Lair</em> both make a few changes to their respective formulas, but as far as actual moment-to-moment gameplay changes go, the ones I want to highlight in particular are <em>Yooka-Laylee</em>'s stamina meter and <em>The Impossible Lair</em>'s health system.</p>
<p><em>Banjo-Kazooie</em> had a wide variety of different moves, some of which consumed collectibles to use. Shooting eggs consumes eggs, flying consumes feathers and becoming invulnerable consumes Golden Feathers, which are rare and can only be carried in stacks of ten. This makes sense in a collectathon and assures that the player will never be able too powerful, but still leaves the possibility for the player to stock up so they can go to town to fart out grenades everywhere if they wish. <em>Yooka-Laylee</em> uses a stamina meter, which slowly refills itself, although it can also be refilled by eating butterflies. Most of the time, however, there aren't any butterflies around, so most of your fun or important moves (particularly rolling, which makes you go much faster and lets you roll up most steep hills) simply make you wait in-between uses. The stamina meter <em>can</em> be upgraded, but it's still bizarre that a 3D platformer would ever make you wait to use the fun moves.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/yooka_laser.jpg" alt="Yooka-Laylee using the Camo Cloak ability to reflect sunlight" />
<em>It doesn't help that Yooka-Laylee's moves have lacking instructions, which this <a href="https://youtu.be/tOqtaW_Gico?t=265">great Design Doc video</a> goes over. For the longest time, I had no clue the Camo Cloak ability lets you reflect lasers.</em></p>
<p>Moving forward a bit, in the old <em>Donkey Kong Country</em> games, your partner acts as your health bar. You play as two Kongs at a time. When you get hit you lose the Kong you're playing as, who gets replaced by the Kong in back. If you don't have a Kong at your side, you die and lose a life, and starting from DKC2 if you had both Kongs you could do some special bonus moves, like throwing your partner around. <em>The Impossible Lair</em> does something similar with its Laylee system, which works like this: you play as Yooka with Laylee sitting on you, similar to <em>Donkey Kong Country Returns</em> and <em>Tropical Freeze</em>. If you get hit, Laylee starts flying around in a panic for a few seconds. If you manage to grab her before she flies off-screen, you get her back. If you don't have Laylee, then you lose access to both the Twirl Jump and Buddy Slam moves, and you get hit you die and respawn at the last checkpoint as well as lose some Quills. You can also get Laylee back by ringing a Dingbat, which can be occassionally found in levels.</p>
<p>While it's an interesting idea to let the player shrug off damage if they recover quickly enough, most of the time it's a rather frustrating system to deal with. Laylee moves quickly and erratically, like <a href="https://youtu.be/O6zkGU3-OVI?t=4148">Baby Mario on speed</a>, and without the right Tonic she flies off rather quickly as well. Back when I first played <em>The Impossible Lair</em> she also had a habit of getting stuck on level terrain or even clipping into it sometimes. I don't know if that was ever fixed, but getting Laylee back in any level segment that's cramped or filled with enemies ended up almost never being worth the attempt.</p>
<p>But the biggest problem with this health system isn't even that, it's that you <em>need</em> Laylee to obtain a few of the TWIT coins. Scattered through each level are four collectible coins, and a lot of these tends to be in either situations that don't let you attempt to get it a second time (like when the level doesn't let you backtrack by cutting you off with a one-way door, or when you need to jump off an enemy that doesn't respawn) or requires Laylee to get it. It was never not painful when I ditched her because she got stuck somewhere I couldn't reach, only to realize I couldn't get the next TWIT coin because it was underneath something I needed to Buddy Slam. You could just shrug off these coins as not being worth the effort, but they are <em>mandatory for progress</em>. You need to pay Trowzer in TWIT coins in order to get past the various Paywalls on the overworld.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/yooka_overworld.jpg" alt="The overworld in Yooka-Laylee and The Impossible Lair" />
<em>Funnily enough, the overworld itself is probably the best part of The Impossible Lair despite the Paywalls. It kinda made me want to see Playtonic tackle a full-on Yooka-Laylee puzzle spin-off.</em></p>
<p>Both the stamina meter and the Laylee system don't even impact the moment-to-moment gameplay that much, but they're still the biggest changes these games make, and whenever they do have an impact they're usually a source of frustration. That really is a shame, because there is plenty they could've done instead to shake up the formula in these games. Seeing as your main character is a chameleon, why not build the game around his tongue? In the first game you use Yooka's tongue to eat butterflies to refill health/stamina and eat objects to gain their properties like a timed powerup, and in the second game it's how you grab objects. It'd be much more interesting if they built the whole game around it, letting you latch onto walls to jump off or grab onto grappling hooks to swing around levels. Those are absolutely not original ideas, but they work. Either way, as long as <em>Yooka-Laylee</em> and <em>The Impossible Lair</em> had some notable mechanic that shook up the moment-to-moment gameplay, they could've avoided most of the comparisons people keep making with the Rare games of old. They could've even stood side by side with them.</p>
<p>The saddest part is that <em>Yooka-Laylee</em> could've been just an awkward first step as the franchise figures out what it tries to do. Many classic game franchises only started taking off after their second or third installment, after all. The thing about impressions in this industry is that for the public, the first game of a franchise is what it <em>can</em> be, but the second game is what it <em>should</em> be. <em>Yooka-Laylee</em> could have made an easy recovery as long as the next Yooka game they showed off was something new and unexpected, even if it wasn't the sequel. The problem was they announced <em>The Impossible Lair</em> instead. Even though it's a pretty good idea to use some of the original game's assets to make a lower budget spin-off so you have some more funds for the sequel, and even though some people - myself included - were excited by that game's announcement, in the eyes of the public it mostly just cemented the franchise as being a shameless Rare rip-off.</p>
<p>Whatever they do with the next <em>Yooka-Laylee</em> game, I hope they find something to build the whole game around, something that lets it stand on its own merits. That said, no matter how hard the franchise tries to become its own thing from now on, it's going to be very hard to shake off that label.</p>
<p>(Thanks to the Yooka-Laylee Wiki for the in-game screenshots. I've only played these games on the Switch, so I don't have an easy way to take my own.)</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>vertettegd@gmail.com (Vertette)</author>
            <category>Design</category>
            <enclosure url="https://vertette.github.io/img/yooka_overworld.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Pixel Art of Salaryman Shi]]></title>
            <link>https://vertette.github.io/post/pixelartshi</link>
            <guid>https://vertette.github.io/post/pixelartshi</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[It was late 2019. I was bored out of my skull, waiting for DJ Coco to fix up a build for Paperball so I could get back on testing, but I didn't feel like workin...]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It was late 2019. I was bored out of my skull, waiting for DJ Coco to fix up a build for <em>Paperball</em> so I could get back on testing, but I didn't feel like working on any particularly big project at the time. I looked around my hard drive looking for anything to do and found some old mock-up graphics I made for an old, abandoned project. A feeling of nostalgia immediately washed over me.</p>
<p>Back in 2013, me and DJ Coco had plans for a 2D platformer named <em>Rad Dude</em>. <em>Shovel Knight</em> was busy blowing up Kickstarter at the time, and in turn, we were inspired to try and make a sidescroller of our own. It would be an 8-bit love letter to all those old, bizarrely localized games on the NES that felt the need to shove in <strong>MACHO DUDES</strong>, <strong>BADNESS</strong> and everything else <strong>GNARLY</strong> about the 80s. It starred the titular Rad Dude and his best friend, Cool Chick, as they rocked denim clothes and used all kinds of crazy gadgets to rescue the city from an evil toymaker.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/raddude_0.png" alt="Rad Dude concept art" />
<em>I'm rad.</em></p>
<p>I'll spare you the details because, well, there wasn't much more to it than that. DJ Coco quickly abandoned the project after it became clear that the idea was lacking, which angered and saddened me quite a bit. In hindsight, <em>Rad Dude</em> was clearly not going to be anything special. We didn't actually have much experience, money or vision for the game, so it never really had a chance to be anything good with the level of our skills back then. At the time, though, I didn't see it that way. I felt betrayed by my best friend as I thought we were truly onto something. In the end, with not much progress having been made on the game itself, all I was left with was a bunch of ideas and some mock-up graphics as the both of us moved on to other projects.</p>
<p>I took those same old <em>Rad Dude</em> graphics six years later and saved over them, not even caring to keep a back-up of it anywhere. With Mario on my mind at the time - Mario being the first thing I'll draw if I want to draw but don't know what to draw - I mutilated the old pixel art to turn it into an ersatz version of <em>Super Mario Bros.</em>, and suddenly an idea sprang in my mind: I could use these graphics to make a small joke game that would look and feel like a Chinese bootleg developer made their own take on the classic Mario games.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/shi_early_0.png" alt="Early Salaryman Shi concept art" />
<em>Before...</em></p>
<p>I sent the mock-up to DJ Coco, expecting him to find it as funny as I did. Instead, he was unimpressed. &quot;It's pretty on the nose&quot;, he said. &quot;Yeah, that's the point,&quot; I explained. &quot;It's going to be like a bootleg Mario, glitching out at times and whatnot. It'd be funny.&quot; &quot;Honestly, that sounds kinda boring,&quot; he shot back. &quot;I would just rethink the entire idea.&quot; And so I went back to the drawing board, trying to figure out what to do with this mock-up. I did another search through my hard-drive and, by luck, stumbled onto yet another old abandoned project of mine. Suddenly, it hit me. I started giggling, then chuckling, then I burst out in laughter. It was stupid, it was hilarious and it had lots of potential.</p>
<p>After <em>Rad Dude</em>'s death, I started making a game in <em>RPG Maker VX Ace</em>. I had an obsession with <em>Takeshi no Chosenjo</em> at the time and wanted to make something with a similar style and tone, and so I named my game <em>Takeshi's Second Challenge</em>. It would be an RPG starring a salaryman named Takeshi Shi, and it was going to be somewhat unique in that you could only raise stats or earn money by doing minigames. You would increase your stats by working out at the gym and make money by doing various odd jobs. Combine that with the obligatory <em>Dragon Quest</em>-esque battles and a dark, surreal sense of humor and I ended up with a prototype that was surprisingly fun for what it was. (And yes, I do like <em>No More Heroes</em>.)</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/takeshisc_0.png" alt="Takeshi's Second Challenge screenshot" />
<em>I had to hook up my old PC to take a screenshot of this.</em></p>
<p>The problem with <em>Takeshi's Second Challenge</em>, however, is that while I loved the idea, I didn't have the programming or art skills to do the idea justice. While it was fun to work in RPG Maker to try to push the limits of the engine as far as I could, I quickly ran into issues as the scope of the game became too big for me to handle. I didn't know how to program the engine into doing what I wanted it to do, didn't have the art skills to make it look as good as I envisioned it to be and didn't have the budget to compensate for either of these shortcomings. That's why I reluctantly decided to shelf the game indefinitely, planning to return to the game one day in the future.</p>
<p>And so, years later, I sketched up a bored looking Takeshi Shi, some boxes, a ladder and some bills, put them into the mock-up and sent the result to DJ Coco, who couldn't stop laughing either. We quickly started throwing ideas around: how the game would play, what kind of power-ups it would have, what the goal would be and so on. It didn't take long until we agreed to turn this into a real game after he was done developing <em>Paperball</em>, which we were sure wouldn't take that long. An actual <strong>year and a half</strong> later, after various patches, three DLC packs and a <em>Nintendo Switch</em> port, we would finally begin work on <em>Salaryman Shi</em>.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/shi_early_1.png" alt="Early Salaryman Shi concept art" />
<em>...and after.</em></p>
<p>As you can see, the game was originally going to be 8-bit just like <em>Rad Dude</em>, but I quickly changed my mind on this for two simple reasons: 1) it's boring and 2) %&amp;$#ing stop it already. Shi could never hope to stand out in the ocean of identical looking 2D 8-bit platformers on <em>Steam</em>. I started experimenting with making a 16-bit art style for the game, which is the first time I tried to draw actual 16-bit art that wasn't just replicating another game's art style, but my earliest attempts were so bad DJ Coco rejected them on the spot. That was surprising, as he can be harsh, but he's usually not <em>that</em> harsh. He suggested simply going back to an 8-bit style, but I was too stubborn to do that. I knew I had it in me to challenge myself and put out a game that would, at the very least, not embarass me with its visuals.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/shi_early_2.png" alt="Early Salaryman Shi concept art" />
<em>How are you going to accomplish that? Definitely not like this. Yuck.</em></p>
<p>Yet the longer I tried to develop Shi's art style, the more I felt frustrated at myself. I knew I was capable of at least putting out competent art, but it still wasn't clicking for me. All the art I was putting out was garbage. I tried various different drawing tools just to see if something would change, and that's when the light bulb finally blinked on: the only times I've ever tried to make pixel art more complex than in an NES game is when I was working on ROM hacks. Somehow, that was the big difference. I installed YY-CHR and Lunar Magic, started putting a palette together and quickly drew up a few mock-ups after. I showed the results to DJ Coco, who said: &quot;looks OK but could be a bit more original&quot;. Now we were finally getting somewhere.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/shi_early_3.png" alt="Early Salaryman Shi concept art" />
<em>That's right, there was a time where Shi looked even more like Super Mario World.</em></p>
<p>In that sense, <em>Salaryman Shi</em>'s look isn't just accurate to 16-bit era visuals, it <em>works on actual 16-bit hardware</em>. Outside of the use of a few transformative effects (which could still be replicated with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_FX">Super FX chip</a>), everything about it works with the real SNES's limits: the RGB values, the amount of colors per palette row and total palette rows, even the amount of VRAM dictacting how many unique tiles can be used at a given time. I could rave about this stuff for hours, but I'll spare you from the exact technical details. TL;DGAF: Shi's art works on the SNES.</p>
<p>Now the obvious question is, why would I go through all that trouble for something that's so trivial that nobody will ever notice and/or appreciate it? The answer might surprise you - it's because it made it easier to draw. The paradox of limitations is that, when you set some hard limitations for yourself, it becomes easier to be creative. After all, having no limitations at all means anything is on the table. Limitations, on the other hand, make it very easy to determine what you can and can't do. As an indie developer who's seen dozens of people burn themselves out with crazy ambitious ideas and scope creep, I've found that not many artists in this industry embrace their limitations. They get it in their head that their first game <em>needs</em> to have a scope bigger and more ambitious than they could reasonably take on. It's a mistake that, as you can reasonably assume from <em>Salaryman Shi</em>'s complicated history, I've made many times myself.</p>
<p>And yet it really doesn't have to be that way. That's the great thing about independent games: there's much less pressure to deliver something big and perfectly polished because consumers don't expect that most indie developers  have the budget for that (unless your game is priced appropiately). If it's decent, people will forgive it for not being very unique. And if it's a bit rough, people won't mind as long as you're trying something new. It really is that simple.</p>
<p><em>Salaryman Shi</em> went on to sell about 1.400 copies. That's nothing to brag about, but it was never going to be a game that'd rock the industry or something that'd change the way people look at games, and it was never meant to be. It was a small game that me and DJ Coco made in our spare time for fun. Because our plans were never that ambitious, it was easy to just keep working on it, knowing that the final game would be done Real Soon Now™. The base game ended up only taking a year to develop, with the free DLC only taking a few extra months on top, and with its budget being so low we ended up making a pretty decent profit off it.</p>
<p>If you stop thinking of limitations as what you can't do, but instead as what you <em>can</em>, everything becomes much easier.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>vertettegd@gmail.com (Vertette)</author>
            <category>Pixel art</category>
            <enclosure url="https://vertette.github.io/img/shi_early_1.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Character Design of Paperball]]></title>
            <link>https://vertette.github.io/post/designpaperball</link>
            <guid>https://vertette.github.io/post/designpaperball</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2023 12:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Were Paperball's character designs a success? It's a hard question to answer for me.  I remember waking up early one morning and finding a message on my phone....]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Were <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1198510/Paperball/"><em>Paperball</em></a>'s character designs a success? It's a hard question to answer for me.</p>
<p>I remember waking up early one morning and finding a message on my phone. &quot;Vinny is playing Paperball&quot;, a friend told me. &quot;Holy crap&quot;, I replied. I rushed onto my computer to check Twitch and there it was, Vinny from Vinesauce was in fact <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5ls_bRPNyes">playing <em>Paperball</em></a>, the game that I had been helping my best friend <a href="https://twitter.com/CliaxGamesCoco/">DJ Coco</a> develop for the past year or so.</p>
<p>It was a surreal moment to say the least, seeing a streamer I loved so much play a game I've been involved with, but even weirder was all the attention we suddenly got. Cliax Games never really had a huge audience, so this was new for us. We got a bunch of fan art, some of it affectionate and some of it tongue in cheek, but more important was all the feedback we received. &quot;It looks low budget&quot;, yeah, I mean, it was. &quot;It's a bit slow&quot;, that's fair, something to consider for next time? &quot;Where's the pants&quot;, &quot;why doesn't she wear pants&quot;, &quot;why is the cat wearing FMB boots&quot;, &quot;no pants&quot;...</p>
<p>Looks like I made a mistake.</p>
<p>Back in late 2018, DJ Coco showed me a screenshot of the game he was working on. He called it <em>Paperball</em>, and he said it was inspired by the <em>Super Monkey Ball</em> games, which he is a big fan of. He explained that, as the series hadn't seen a mainline game in years, he wanted to make his own successor with some additional mechanics from games like <em>Trackmania</em>. It was probably gonna be a small game, 50 levels at most, but it should be a fun little side-project. &quot;Cool&quot;, I said. I was either distracted or unimpressed at the time. Probably both.</p>
<p>The more he showed me of <em>Paperball</em>, however, the more I realized something. <em>Monkey Ball</em> was considered dead at the time, another sad relic of Sega's better days among franchises like <em>Jet Set Radio</em> and <em>Crazy Taxi</em>. There were other marble rollers on the market like <em>Marble Blast Ultra</em>, but all of them missed that arcade-like simplicity that made <em>Monkey Ball</em> such a fun game to pick up and play, and <em>Rolled Out</em> hadn't even launched its <a href="https://www.indiegogo.com/projects/rolled-out/">IndieGoGo campaign</a> yet. That gave me an idea.</p>
<p>&quot;I want to help you market the game&quot;, I told DJ Coco. &quot;This is a game which could definitely fill a hole no other game on the market does right now, and if marketed in the right way, I can see it selling very well. Thousands of copies, with some luck. The first thing we need, though, is a mascot. You can't market a game with a paper ball for a mascot.&quot; &quot;Yeah yeah, I know&quot;, he said, &quot;'don't worry, I'll whip up something.&quot; He showed me his something a few weeks later.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/coco_0.png" alt="Early Coco concept art" />
<em>A Coco that never was, thankfully.</em></p>
<p>I don't remember what I said, but I'm sure it had to involve insults of some kind because this design still haunts me. &quot;What are you going for here?&quot;, I remember asking. &quot;What are any of these elements supposed to communicate? Why is she even wearing a graduation cap?&quot; &quot;Because she's an art college student&quot;, DJ Coco explained. &quot;But she hasn't graduated yet&quot;, I replied with some bafflement. &quot;And why the gloves, or giant bell, or striped tail, or those socks?&quot;</p>
<p>He couldn't really explain any of his creative decisions, which isn't a good sign. He was inspired by the design of the shopkeeper in <em>Blinx: The Time Sweeper</em>, he told me later, but failed to bring the design together in any way that would communicate anything about this character.</p>
<p>&quot;Right&quot;, I said. &quot;I'm redoing this stupid thing, because there's no way you will sell anything with a mascot that looks like this. This bright pink is dreadful, let's give her a blue shirt and hot pink pants instead. Let's give her a beret and scarf to show she's an art student, and get rid of the gloves and all the stripes because it just makes the design too busy. Just keep the tip white.&quot; I sent a picture of what I came up with to DJ Coco, and while he was happy with the result, he insisted on adding boots and a cat bell to the end of the scarf. &quot;Sure, that's fine&quot;, I replied.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/coco_1.png" alt="Later Coco concept art" />
<em>A Coco that sorta was.</em></p>
<p>It is entirely my fault that I never stressed the pants more, as I drew the shirt over the pants in my initial drawing and DJ Coco used that as a reference for the concept art that we would end up sending to the actual 2D artist. At the time, I figured it wasn't a big deal because she's a cartoon cat, and anthromorphic cartoons almost exclusively dress in halves anyway. I'm sure it's due to the game's 2D art looking more anime-inspired than I had envisioned that it became such a focal point, but by the time I realized this it was too late to object.</p>
<p>Some credit has to go to the 2D artist, though, for simplifying the design's face and giving her some eyebrows as it helped a lot with expressions. I don't know who made the suggestion to turn the bell red, but it ended up reminding everyone of Pokéballs so while it ties in well with the design of the playable ball itself, we probably should've kept the pink. Thankfully, Nintendo has never had any legal objections to our games so far, which I admit sorta surprises me.</p>
<p>The name was easier to figure out, defying industry conventions. &quot;Let's call her Coco the Cat&quot;, I said. &quot;It's short, it fits the character's slightly ditzy personality and it works with the <em>Monkey Ball</em> naming conventions. AiAi, Baby, Coco and so on.&quot; &quot;Don't you think people would assume we just named her after me?&quot;, DJ Coco asked. &quot;Eh, that's not a big deal. You created the game, and she created the <em>Paperball</em> art project in-game, it fits.&quot; And that was that.</p>
<p>The game released on March 27th 2020 and ended up surpassing our expectations quite a bit. Part of that is due to a lot of luck: I had contacted various YouTubers and streamers, ones I knew were big <em>Monkey Ball</em> fans, to ask if they wanted a copy. Some of them actually replied and ended up streaming the game, raising a lot of awareness, and as a result other YouTubers and streamers ended up actually contacting <em>us</em> to ask for a copy. That was a first.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/djgray_0.png" alt="Betty from DJ Gray" />
<em><a href="https://djgraycomic.com/comic/dj-gray-page-303/">In an alternate universe</a>, Paperball sold well enough to get merchandise.</em></p>
<p>Of course, these days just releasing a game doesn't mean you're done with it, not by a long shot, so it didn't take long until plans for post-release content were made. The initial plan was to develop one new game mode and two new DLC packs, with their own art, gimmicks and environments, but just like with the main game - which launched with three times as many levels as planned - DJ Coco's scope got bigger and bigger, so I ended up having to design three new outfits for the DLC packs.</p>
<p>(Fun fact: Blitz Mode - named after <em>Super Monkey Ball Banana Blitz</em>, which infamously added a jump - and Flip Mode - where you try to control one ball with two players - were my ideas. I suggested them as jokes, and DJ Coco ended up implementing both. I should have known better as he had similarly added the Fallout Royale achievement, unlocked by getting 76.000 fallouts, based on a <em>Fallout 76</em> joke I made before release. I don't make jokes around him anymore.)</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/coco_2.png" alt="Coco's DLC outfits concept art" />
<em>In my defense, some people pay good money to dress up anthromorphic characters.</em></p>
<p>The new outfits were a cakewalk to design in comparison to Coco's original design. The toughest part was already done, so I just had to draw some new outfits. I originally wanted to go with a more 60's kitschy kind of look for the Secret Spy outfit, but it was too hard to draw and didn't really fit the <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1209620/Paperball__Secret_Spy_Pack/">environment of the pack</a> so I ended up going with something more muted with a touch of pink. The <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1209621/Paperball__Deep_Sea_Pack/">mermaid</a> and <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1285150/Paperball__Cherry_Sky_Pack/">kimono</a> outfits were even easier as they're admittedly not particularly inspired designs, although DJ Coco did have to &quot;motivate&quot; me to finish them on time by drawing intentionally bad art and threatening to send it to the 2D artist.</p>
<p>What was trickier to figure out were the poses - I didn't want each pack to just have the same art with a new costume slapped on top, so I had to think hard of some new ones that would still fit the character. My initial suggestion for the Deep Sea pack's game over pose was Coco getting jabbed in the back by a fishing hook, but DJ Coco didn't like how violent it looked even if depicted in a cartoony way, so it became more of a hook entrapment. I feel it's a weaker pose, but it was probably the right call.</p>
<p>It was during the summer of 2020, right during development of the DLC, that we were trying to bring <em>Paperball</em> to Nintendo Switch. We applied to Nintendo's developer program and got rejected, and with both us and the fans wanting to see the game appear on the platform, it seemed there was no real other way than to get a publisher. The company we had gotten in contact with had a good reputation and saw potential in the game, but they insisted on a five dollar price tag and a large cut of the profits (which according to my knowledge now was actually <strong>below average</strong>).</p>
<p>Between the publisher, the platform and taxes we would've seen maybe half a dollar per sale, and for how much work the game ended up being, that just didn't seem worth it. During the talks, we ended up applying to Nintendo again and somehow got approved this time. While their reasons for changing their mind are still beyond me, it was now official - <em>Paperball</em> was getting a Nintendo Switch release. But how do we incentivize people to double dip?</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/chrissy_0.png" alt="Chrissy concept art" />
<em>Of course! We add more furry cats! Cliax Games, you've done it again.</em></p>
<p>DJ Coco came up with a plan: we would release the new patch with extra content and DLC packs in September 2020, and then continue working on the Nintendo Switch port, hopefully being done around January 2021 with a release in March, one year after the original game. The idea was to release the port under the name <em>Paperball Deluxe</em>, including all the DLC and some timed console-exclusive content: a new pack of levels with new world themes, music, gimmicks and a new mascot character, which I volunteered to design.</p>
<p>After all the feedback we got on regular <em>Paperball</em>, I felt a bit more self-aware about designing something good for <em>Paperball Deluxe</em>. My first thought was to make a hippie character, as the new levels were going to be sunflower themed, so it seemed fitting enough. I ended up doing a lot more research - both into hippie fashion and character design - for the final character design, which ended up taking a lot of inspiration from various places: the sunflower headband and the beads were inspired by some photos I found, the yellow jacket was inspired by Athena Cykes from <em>Ace Attorney</em>, and the boots were something I threw in because I wanted some earthy colors in there.</p>
<p>I presented DJ Coco with the three designs you see above, and he chose the green palette for tying in well with the sunflower theme. I agreed, for both that reason and because the yellow and green contrasts well against Coco's pink and blue. The only touch-up I made after this was increasing the color contrast and giving her a brown belt as I felt something was missing, and it tied the boots in better with the rest of the design. DJ Coco named her Chrissy (get it? Chris and Coco?), and that was that. <em>Paperball Deluxe</em> ended up releasing March 25th 2021, using that exact design.</p>
<p><img src="https://vertette.github.io/img/chrissy_1.png" alt="Chrissy's final design" />
<em>The loose hanging belt and shaggy hair also helped sell Chrissy as more of a slob than her sister. In a game where you don't have much time to show the character's personalities, every tiny bit counts.</em></p>
<p>I was a lot happier with Chrissy's design for many reasons, the biggest one being she's not pantsless. The second biggest reason is that her design simply is a lot stronger. Her design communicates her personality much better than Coco's, while still wearing an outfit that looks like something a real person would actually wear. The only big mistake I made was the peace necklace, which I forgot should have three lines near the bottom instead of two. Nobody except DJ Coco ever pointed this out, though, and it took him years to realize. My headcanon is that Chrissy bought it from some cheap vendor and was too dumb to notice. Man, how embarrassing would that be!</p>
<p>(On a side note, I was also very happy with Chrissy's voice work. Coco and Chrissy are both voiced by <a href="https://twitter.com/AimeeSmithVA">Aimee Smith</a>, an absolute sweetheart of a woman who has done voicework for many notable games, and also <em>Paperball</em>. She nailed Coco's voice, which sounds appropiately bubbly, but we weren't sure if she could do the voice we had in mind for Chrissy. We gave her a few notes - Chrissy was a more laid-back old sister character with a whispery voice, and asked her if she thought she could do it. She ended up delivering the exact voice we wanted, much to our delight.)</p>
<p>So, to go back to my question at the beginning. Were the designs a success? My thoughts on the matter are complex, but I can't deny that, at the end of the day, the characters helped sell <em>Paperball</em>. I've seen people replying to fan art online expressing their interest in the game, and I've read reviews that admit they bought the game entirely because of the designs. That's what good designs should do, really, so the short answer is: yes, with a but.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>vertettegd@gmail.com (Vertette)</author>
            <category>Character design</category>
            <enclosure url="https://vertette.github.io/img/coco_1.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
            <link>https://vertette.github.io/post/helloworld</link>
            <guid>https://vertette.github.io/post/helloworld</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2023 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Welcome to my blog, my name is Christopher Stephens. By day I do boring IT work, by night I work on games. I've worked on games like Paperball, Salaryman Shi an...]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my blog, my name is Christopher Stephens. By day I do boring IT work, by night I work on games. I've worked on games like <em>Paperball</em>, <em>Salaryman Shi</em> and <em>Onlink</em>. (They're not very well known so don't think you've been living under a rock if you've never heard of them.) This blog is where I'll put up articles discussing and/or analyzing video games from a developer's perspective. Some of the games I'll talk about will be ones I've been involved with developing, though not all of them.</p>
<p>I've been meaning to write down all the thoughts I've had about games over the years instead of bothering my friends with them. For the longest time I've been tempted to start making YouTube videos, actually, but writing takes up a lot less time and effort, plus there's no risk of Google's faulty bots slapping me around this way. Hopefully someone on the internet still appreciates written material, and hopefully some of these articles will inform and/or entertain you.</p>
<p>I'll try to write something every two weeks at the very least, but we'll see how that turns out.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>vertettegd@gmail.com (Vertette)</author>
            <category>Other</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>